sahajmarg.org 2013-04-01

# Sahaj Marg Raja Yoga Meditation - Privacy Policy

## Introduction

This is the policy of the Shri Ram Chandra Mission of India and its national and regional Shri Ram Chandra Mission sister organisations throughout the world (hereafter collectively referred to as SRCM ) concerning the personal information that they collect, store and process of their members ( abhyasis ) and other persons.

## Restrictions on use of the content

No content from this site may be copied, framed, reproduced, republished, uploaded, posted, transmitted, or distributed in any way, except that you may temporarily download one copy of the content on any single computer or print one or more copies of the content for your personal, noncommercial use only, provided you keep intact all copyright, trademark and other proprietary notices.

## Objectives of this privacy policy

This privacy policy seeks to achieve that the personal information that SRCM collects, processes and stores of its members is:

  1. Fairly and lawfully processed.
  2. Processed for limited purposes.
  3. Adequate, relevant and not excessive.
  4. Accurate.
  5. Kept no longer than necessary.
  6. Processed in accordance with the data subject’s rights.
  7. Secure.
  8. Transferred only to sister organisations with adequate protection.
  9. Transferred only to third parties with permission from the data subject or as required by law.

## Collection and processing

Persons that apply for membership of SRCM provide personal information. This information is stored in a database of members worldwide and processed in relation to membership administration, issuing of membership cards, and in relation to the services that SRCM provides to its members, such as participation at satsangh, seminars and other events, and sales of and subscriptions to books, magazines and other articles. This personal information is stored and when needed processed as long as the person remains a member of SRCM.

Up to 2012, the database of members worldwide was located in India for members residing in India, and located in a data centers in India and the United States for members not residing in India. (Prospective) members filled out paper forms; this information was entered at national or regional level in spreadsheets, and sent via email to USA which may be forwarded to India (in case of prospective members not residing in India), where it was entered into the database. For members residing in India, the information on the paper forms was directly entered into the database by coordinators. This system will be phased out during 2012.

In 2012, a new data management system will gradually be introduced, located in the USA, with the name AIMS (Abhyasi Information Management System). AIMS will be installed in one or more servers owned and rented at data centers located in India and the USA.

For most countries, an online interface ( web form ) will enable persons to apply for registration as member of SRCM and for a membership card directly with AIMS in the USA. Certain specific information will be forwarded to a vendor located in India where the Membership Card will be produced. For some countries, paper forms may continue to be used, before the data is entered into AIMS. SRCM issues membership cards, which are manufactured in India.

For India, paper forms will be used for the foreseeable future; the information on the paper forms will be entered into the database by coordinators.  However, SRCM may, when appropriate, choose to utilize the web form for Indian members who are able to submit their details online.

In addition, SRCM occasionally processes personal data related to non-members (e.g., family or friends of members that participate in events or hold subscriptions to magazines or book series). This data may be submitted by the persons themselves or by others, e.g., a member of SRCM submitting registration information for a seminar for his family, or giving a magazine subscription as a present to a family member.

In addition, SRCM may process data related to former members, e.g., when they maintain subscriptions to SRCM magazines or other publications after their membership has expired. Certain specific information will be forwarded to a vendor located in India where the publication subscriptions, audio, video, photographs and other print media are produced and distributed under license fro SRCM.

For the purposes of registration for events or subscriptions to journals or books, the relevant personal information in the membership database may be accessed or copied to facilitate the registration or subscription process.

In addition, SRCM shall process data related to Prefect Lists. This information is shared with the President and other responsible functionaries of the Mission.

If SRCM wants to use personal information for any purpose not described in this Privacy Policy, it will ask for prior consent.

## Updating and correction

SRCM strives to update any out-dated information and correct any inaccurate information. When the personal information of members of SRCM has changed, e.g., in case of change of address, or when their data needs correction, members are requested to submit an on-line notification form, available at [https://www.srcm.org/ssl/changeaddr.jsp](https://www.srcm.org/ssl/changeaddr.jsp)

## Deletion

Personal data stored and processed in relation to a particular event or to subscriptions will be deleted when no longer needed in relation to the organisation of the event or the subscription. This will happen at the latest 2 years after the end of the event or 2 years after the termination of the subscription, unless there is a requirement for longer retention under applicable law.

Local SRCM centres may ask participants in satsangh and other events to sign a register of participants (‘golden book’). These registers are kept as a record of attendance and are destroyed at the latest 10 years after they are full or no longer used.

When a person terminates his/her membership of SRCM, his/her personal information is deleted, in as far as not still required for specific purposes, e.g., in conjunction with recent participation in events, ongoing subscriptions, or processing of donations. Upon request of such a person, his/her personal data will be deleted forthwith if it is not otherwise required to be retained by applicable law.

In order to request deletion of personal information from the membership database, you can use the notification form mentioned above. If you would like confirmation that your personal information has been deleted from the membership database, please contact the Data Protection Officer for your region.

## Transfer of personal information to third parties

SRCM does not make personal information available to third parties for commercial purposes.

SRCM may make relevant personal information available to third parties in the following cases: (i) in relation to services that have been explicitly requested, e.g., to a hotel where persons who participate in an event are staying, or to a courier service for delivery of journals, books, or identity cards; (ii) to public authorities when we have a belief in good faith that disclosure of such information is necessary to satisfy an applicable law, regulation, legal process or enforceable governmental request, e.g., to local government or police authorities who require a list of participants of a particular event; (iii) to address fraud or security issues, or protect against harm the rights, property or safety of SRCM, its members or the general public as required or permitted by applicable law.

For any transfer of personal data to third parties that does not happen in relation to these cases, SRCM will seek prior consent.

## Transfer of personal data to SRCM organisations in different countries

SRCM processes personal information in conjunction with this Privacy Policy in different countries worldwide, e.g., when seminars or gatherings are held in those countries. All SRCM sister organisations, including the Sahaj Marg Spirituality Foundation, to which personal information is transferred under this Privacy Policy, adhere to the same high standard of protection described in this Privacy Policy and will handle the information in accordance with this Privacy Policy and applicable laws and regulations.

SRCM complies with the US-EU Safe Harbor Principles and the US-Swiss Safe Harbor Principles as set forth by the Department of Commerce of the USA regarding the collection, use, and retention of personal information from European Union member countries and Switzerland.

## Internet use: cookies, logs and user communications

When you visit SRCM websites, we may send cookies to your computer or other device. We may use cookies to improve the quality of our web service, in particular for storing user preferences. Most browsers are initially set up to accept cookies, but you can reset your browser to refuse all cookies or to indicate when a cookie is being sent.

When you access SRCM websites via a browser, application or other client our servers may record certain information. These server logs may include information such as your web request, your interaction with a service, browser type, browser language, the date and time of your request and one or more cookies that may identify your browser. These server logs are deleted at the latest after 2 years.

When you send email or other communications to SRCM, we may retain those communications in order to process your inquiries, respond to your requests and improve our services. We may use your email address to communicate with you about our services.

## Security and enforcement

We take appropriate security measures to protect against unauthorised access to or unauthorised alteration, disclosure or destruction of data. These include password protection, appropriate encryption of sensitive data, and internal reviews of our data collection, storage and processing practices and security measures.

We restrict access to personal information to organisers that are members of SRCM. Controlled access will be assured through OpenERP open source software, which has been customized for SRCM use. SRCM organisers will only be able to view the data in AIMS pertaining to members in the geographical area for which they bear responsibility, and will not have access to data pertaining to other areas. A few coordinators with responsibilities for SRCM globally (e.g., the President of SRCM) or for the functioning of AIMS (system administrators) will have access to the entire database.

All persons of SRCM having access to all or part of AIMS will sign a declaration saying that they will treat the data to which they have access confidentially, and will. not collect, process or use the personal data without authorisation. /p>

## Data Protection Officers

SRCM regularly reviews its compliance with this Privacy Policy and with applicable laws and regulations. The SRCM Data Protection Officers ensure the implementation of this Privacy Policy and the applicable law for their region. If you have any comments on the Privacy Policy of SRCM, please feel free to send an email to the SRCM Data Protection Officer for your region.

Region | Data Protection Officer | Email  
---|---|---  
Africa Anglophone| Devan Leon Reddy| [devan.reddy@nsn.com](mailto:devan.reddy@nsn.com)  
Africa Francophone| Jeanne Nanitelamio| [jnanitelamio@gmail.com](mailto:jnanitelamio@gmail.com)  
Africa Islands| Michel Rasamy| [rasamy@moov.mg](mailto:rasamy@moov.mg)  
Canada, USA, Caribbean & Latin America| Krishna Linga| [krishnalinga.us@gmail.com](mailto:krishnalinga.us@gmail.com)  
Europe, with the exception of Germany| Pierre Studer| [pierrestuder@me.com](mailto:pierrestuder@me.com)  
Far East| B.S. Venkatesh| [bsvenks@gmail.com](mailto:bsvenks@gmail.com)  
Former CIS| Victoriya Afanasyeva| [rusrcm@yahoo.com](mailto:rusrcm@yahoo.com)  
Germany| Heidrun Maeter| [De.secretary@srcm.org](mailto:De.secretary@srcm.org)  
Greater China| Jennifer Ge| [jingfang.ge@yahoo.cn](mailto:jingfang.ge@yahoo.cn)  
India & South Asia| Ashish Singh| [ashish.singh@srcm.org](mailto:ashish.singh@srcm.org)  
Middle East| M.B. Eswaran| [mbeswaran@gmail.com](mailto:mbeswaran@gmail.com)  
Oceania| Timothy Jolley| [timothyjolley@yahoo.com](mailto:timothyjolley@yahoo.com)  
Global Prefects List| Santosh Khanjee| [Santosh@srcm.org](mailto:Santosh@srcm.org)  
  
The SRCM Chief Data Protection Officer, who coordinates the work of the Data Protection Officers and ensures the implementation of this Privacy Policy concerning the database of members worldwide, is Sanjay Sehgal, email [gos.it@srcm.org](mailto:gos.it@srcm.org).

## Changes to this Privacy Policy

This Privacy Policy may change from time to time, e.g., to take account of changes in applicable laws, new services to members of SRCM, or changes in the organisation of SRCM. SRCM will not reduce the rights its members have under this Privacy Policy without their consent. SRCM will post any changes to this Privacy Policy on this page. For significant changes there will be a notice, e.g., an announcement on the SRCM home page and/or in newsletters, or an email notification.
